Guide to the Cornell University ceramics, glassware, and metalware collection, 1893-2003.
Cornell University ceramics, glassware, and metalware collection,
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Cornell University ceramics, glassware, and metalware collection, 1893-2003
41-7-1964. Division of Rare and Manuscript Col
Cornell University. Alumni Association.
18.1 cubic feet
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
The Cornell University Ceramics, Glassware, and Metalware collection consists of items commissioned by the University, fraternities and societies, and departments. Materials include correspondence concerning Cornell Wedgwood china; full sets of Cornell Plates, made by Wedgwood, in Mulberry and blue, with twelve different designs, depicting Cornell scenes and buildings including the Crescent, Sage Chapel, Baker Laboratory, Myron Taylor Hall, Goldwin Smith Hall, Balch Halls, the Clock Tower, the War Memorial, McGraw Hall, Willard Straight Hall, the Ezra Cornell Statue, and Sibley Dome. Also includes a full set of Wedgwood mulberry and blue cups and saucers and an Incomplete set of green saucers and cups.
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
The original set of Cornell plates was created in 1932, based on a design created by E. Stewart Williams (Class of 1933) for the Baird Prize "Place Plate" artwork competition for Design 112, February 1932. The winning design was used by the Wedgwood Company for a set of twelve plates depicting Cornell scenes. Originally created in mulberry, copper green, and Staffordshire blue, they were advertised in the Cornell Alumni News and sold through the Cornell Alumni Corporation. They continued to be advertised and sold through at least 1943. In 1950, they were re-issued.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
The Cornell University Ceramics, Glassware, and Metalware collection consists of items commissioned by the University, fraternities and societies, and departments. Materials include correspondence concerning Cornell Wedgwood china; full sets of Cornell Plates, made by Wedgwood, in Mulberry and blue, with twelve different designs, depicting Cornell scenes and buildings including the Crescent, Sage Chapel, Baker Laboratory, Myron Taylor Hall, Goldwin Smith Hall, Balch Halls, the Clock Tower, the War Memorial, McGraw Hall, Willard Straight Hall, the Ezra Cornell Statue, and Sibley Dome. Also includes a full set of Wedgwood mulberry and blue cups and saucers and an Incomplete set of green saucers and cups.
The collection also contains mugs, cups, and glasses from different class years, reunions, sororities, fraternities, and departments, as well as commemorative plates.
Also, correspondence concerning Cornell Wedgwood china.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Williams, Stewart, 1909-2005.; Cornell University.; Cornell Crew (Rowing team).; Cornell University.Alembic Society.; Cornell University--Athletics.; Cornell University.Class of 1912; Cornell University.Class of 1920; Cornell University.Class of 1936; Cornell University.Class of 1939; Cornell University.Class of 1940; Cornell University.Class of 1944; Cornell University.Class of 1945; Cornell University.Class of 1983; Cornell University.Class of 1987; Cornell University--Societies, etc.; Cosmopolitan Club (Cornell University).; Cornell Law School.; Sigma Alpha Mu.; Tau Delta Eta.; Pi Lambda Phi.
Subjects:
Greek letter societies--New York (State)--Ithaca.; Wedgwood ware.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Wedgwood Plates, Cups, and Saucers
Series II. Cornell Mugs, Cups, and Glasses
Series III. Cornell Plates (non-Wedgwood)
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Wedgwood
  - Subseries Ia. Mulberry Plates
    - Complete set number 1
      - Dinner plate with image of Baker Laboratory of Chemistry, Expression; MU-2307 (Box 2)
      - Dinner plate with image of Balch Hall, 1933-07; MU-2312 (Box 2)
      - Dinner plate with image of The Crescent, 1933-07; MU-2457 (Box 2)
      - Dinner plate with image of Goldwin Smith Hall, 1933-07; MU-988 (Box 2)
      - Dinner plate with image of Library Tower, 1933-07; MU-2319 (Box 2)
      - Dinner plate with image of McGraw Hall, 1933-07; MU-2315 (Box 2)
      - Dinner plate with image of Myron Taylor Hall, 1933-07; MU-860 (Box 3)
      - Dinner plate with image of Sage Chapel, 1933-07; MU-2317 (Box 3)
      - Dinner plate with image of Sibley Dome, 1933-05; MU-2314 (Box 3)
      - Dinner plate with image of statue of Ezra Cornell, 1933-07; MU-2318 (Box 3)
      - Dinner plate with image of the War Memorial, 1933-07; MU-2320 (Box 3)
      - Dinner plate with image of Willard Straight Hall, 1933-07; MU-2313 (Box 3)
    - Complete set number 2
      - Dinner plate with image of Baker Laboratory of Chemistry, 1933-07; MU-854 (Box 4)
      - Dinner plate with image of Balch Hall, 1937-05; MU-2309 (Box 4)
      - Dinner plate with image of The Crescent, 1937-05; MU-1994 (Box 4)
        Missing impressed Wedgewood stamps
      - Dinner plate with image of Goldwin Smith Hall, 1933-05; MU-2306 (Box 4)
      - Dinner plate with image of Library Tower, 1933-07; MU-851 (Box 4)
        Poor condition: cracked down the center with tape holding it together
      - Dinner plate with image of McGraw Hall, 1933-07; MU-856 (Box 4)
      - Dinner plate with image of Myron Taylor Hall, 1937-05; MU-2308 (Box 5)
      - Dinner plate with image of Sage Chapel, 1933-07; MU-855 (Box 5)
      - Dinner plate with image of Sibley Dome, 1933-05; MU-862 (Box 5)
      - Dinner plate with image of statue of Ezra Cornell, 1933-07; MU-858 (Box 5)
      - Dinner plate with image of the War Memorial, 1933-07; MU-853 (Box 5)
      - Dinner plate with image of Willard Straight Hall, 1937-05; MU-1088 (Box 5)
    - Duplicates
      - Dinner plate with image of Baker Laboratory of Chemistry, 1933-07; MU-2458 (Box 6)
      - Dinner plate with image of Baker Laboratory of Chemistry, 1951-12; MU-976 (Box 6)
      - Dinner plate with image of Balch Hall, 1933-07; MU-859 (Box 6)
      - Dinner plate with image of Balch Hall, 1949-10; MU-980 (Box 6)
      - Dinner plate with image of The Crescent, 1933-07; MU-857 (Box 6)
      - Dinner plate with image of Goldwin Smith Hall, 1933-07; MU-861 (Box 6)
      - Dinner plate with image of Library Tower, Undated; MU-978 (Box 7)
      - Dinner plate with image of Library Tower, 1962-03; MU-1996 (Box 7)
      - Dinner plate with image of McGraw Hall, 1933-09; MU-2310 (Box 7)
      - Dinner plate with image of McGraw Hall, 1949-10; MU-995 (Box 7)
    - Dinner plate with image of Myron Taylor Hall, 1933-07; MU-2316 (Box 7)
    - Dinner plate with image of Sage Chapel, 1939-09; MU-1992 (Box 8)
    - Dinner plate with image of Sage Chapel, 1962-03; MU-2122 (Box 8)
    - Dinner plate with image of Sage Chapel, 1959-03; MU-977 (Box 7)
    - Dinner plate with image of Sibley Dome, 1933-09; MU-1993 (Box 8)
    - Dinner plate with image of Sibley Dome, 1941-05; MU-1089 (Box 8)
    - Dinner plate with image of Sibley Dome, 1950-09; MU-979 (Box 8)
    - Dinner plate with image of statue of Ezra Cornell, 1933-12; MU-1995 (Box 8)
    - Dinner plate with image of the War Memorial, 1959-04; MU-2311 (Box 9)
      Chip on lower left
    - Dinner plate with image of the War Memorial, Undated; MU-981 (Box 9)
    - Dinner plate with image of Willard Straight Hall, 1933-07; MU-852 (Box 9)
    - Dinner plate with image of Willard Straight Hall, 1939-09; MU-1997 (Box 9)
  - Subseries Ib. Mulberry Cups and Saucers
    - Saucers, 1937; MU-2357a-2357h (Box 29)
    - Saucers, 1933-1939; MU-2357i-2357j (Box 29)
    - Saucers, 1947-11; MU-2357k-2357n (Box 29)
    - Saucers, 1949-08; MU-2357o (Box 29)
    - Saucer, Undated; MU-2357-p-2357q (Box 30)
    - Tea cup, Undated; MU-2075a-2075q (Box 15,16)
  - Subseries Ic. Blue Plates
    - Dinner plate showing Sibley Dome, 1932-10-06; MU-217 (Box 1)
      First sample plate from the moulds sent to show the shape
    - Complete set number 1
      - Dinner plate with image of Baker Laboratory of Chemistry, 1937-06; MU-2329 (Box 10)
      - Dinner plate with image of Balch Hall, 1937; MU-2328 (Box 10)
        Small chip on back
      - Dinner plate with image of the Crescent, 1937-05; MU-2338 (Box 10)
      - Dinner plate with image of Goldwin Smith Hall, 1937-06; MU-2335 (Box 10)
      - Dinner plate with image of the Library Tower, 1937-06; MU-2330 (Box 10)
      - Dinner plate with image of McGraw Hall, 1934-01; MU-2334 (Box 10)
      - Dinner plate with image of Myron Taylor Hall, 1937-05; MU-2333 (Box 11)
      - Dinner plate with image of Sage Chapel, 1937-06; MU-2326 (Box 11)
      - Dinner plate with image of Sibley Dome, 1937-06; MU-2327 (Box 11)
      - Dinner plate with image of Statue of Ezra Cornell, 1937-06; MU-2332 (Box 11)
      - Dinner plate with image of the War Memorial, 1942; MU-2340 (Box 11)
      - Dinner plate with image of Willard Straight Hall, 1937-06; MU-2336 (Box 11)
    - Duplicates
      - Dinner plate with image of the Crescent, 1944-12; MU-2339 (Box 12)
      - Dinner plate with image of the Crescent, 1950-10; MU-987 (Box 12)
      - Dinner plate with image of Goldwin Smith Hall, 1950-10; MU-984 (Box 12)
      - Dinner plate with image of Goldwin Smith Hall, 1940-03; MU-2325 (Box 12)
      - Dinner plate with image of the Library Tower, 1941-05; MU-2323 (Box 12)
      - Dinner plate with image of the Library Tower, 1944-02; MU-2331 (Box 12)
      - Dinner plate with image of McGraw Hall, 1937-06; MU-2337 (Box 13)
      - Dinner plate with image of McGraw Hall, 1949-10; MU-982 (Box 13)
      - Dinner plate with image of Myron Taylor Hall, 1940-04; MU-2322 (Box 13)
      - Dinner plate with image of Sibley Dome, 1950-10; MU-985 (Box 13)
      - Dinner plate with image of statue of Ezra Cornell, 1941-02; MU-2321 (Box 13)
      - Dinner plate with image of Statue of Ezra Cornell, 1947-02; MU-983 (Box 13)
      - Dinner plate with image of Willard Straight Hall, 1940-1949; MU-2324 (Box 14)
        Dirty, possibly stained
      - Dinner plate with image of Willard Straight Hall, 1947-04; MU-986 (Box 14)
    - Subseries Id. Blue Cups and Saucers
      - Saucers, 1940-08; MU-2358a (Box 28)
      - Saucers, 1944-01; MU-2358b (Box 28)
      - Saucers, 1944-01; MU-2358c (Box 28)
      - Saucers, 1944-02; MU-2358d-2358f (Box 28)
      - Saucers, 1944-02; MU-2358g-2358l (Box 28)
      - Saucers, 1944-03; MU-2358m (Box 28)
      - Saucers, 1947-11; MU-2358n-q (Box 30)
      - Saucer, 1949-08; MU-994a (Box 30)
      - Tea cups, Undated; MU-2076h-2076s (Box 15)
      - Tea cups, Undated; MU-2076a-g (Box 15)
      - Tea cup, Undated; MU-994b (Box 16)
    - Subseries Ie. Green Cups and Saucers
      - Tea cups, Undated; MU-1097a-d (Box 16)
      - Saucers, 1944-02; MU-2359a-2359d (Box 30)
      - Saucers, 1947-11; MU-2359e (Box 30)
- Series II. Cornell Mugs, Cups, and Glasses
  - Subseries IIa. Class Mugs and Glasses
    - Cream ceramic mug with red "Cornell, 1901", 1901; MU-2343, MU-1365 (Box 21)
    - Ivory ceramic mug with red "1906", 1906; MU-2464 (Box 21)
    - Senior Stunt at the Dutch mug, 1908; MU-2346 (Box 19)
    - Senior Smoker mug, 1908; MU-2460 (Box 19)
    - Sophomore Stunt at the Dutch, 1910; MU-1227 (Box 19)
      Cream mug with man smoking and drinking
    - Sophomore Stunt mug, 1911; MU-2362 (Box 21)
      Cream mug with image of man smoking
    - Junior Feed at the dutch, 1911; MU-2365 (Box 21)
    - Stunt mug, 1912; MU-2462, MU-2364 (Box 19)
      Cream mug with men cheering, sitting on red "12"
    - Junior Feed mug, 1912; MU-2367 (Box 20)
      Red mug with man with beer in white
    - Junior Feed mug, 1913; MU-846-847 (Box 20)
      Cream mug with image of man in tie
    - Sophomore Stunt mug, 1913; MU-2363 (Box 20)
      Cream mug with image of waiter
    - Cornell Smoker, St. Louis, 1913; MU-1226 (Box 20)
    - Sophomore Stunt mug, 1914; MU-2361 (Box 20)
      Cream mug with man sitting on beer barrel
    - Junior Feed mug, 1915; MU-1126 (Box 21)
      Cream mug with red "Junior Feed" and caricature of a black waiter
    - Sophomore smoker mug, 1915; MU-1125 (Box 19)
    - Cornell Smoker, St. Louis mug, 1908; MU-2390 (Box 21)
      Cream mug with dark red writing
    - Class of 1920 sophomore smoker mug, 1918; MU-2463 (Box 20)
    - Class of 1912 45th reunion tumbler, 1957; MU-2350a-2350b (Box 17)
      "Enjoy yourself, It's later than you think" written in green
    - Ballantine beer class of 1936 reunion tin mug, 1961; MU-2375 (Box 22)
    - Cornell Class of 1939 25th reunion bottle, 1964; MU-2370 (Box 17)
      Genesee Beer bottle with 4 images of Cornell
    - Cornell Class of 1940 25th reunion tankard, made from pewter, MU-1233 (Box 20)
    - Cornell Class of 1944 25th class reunion, 1969-06-12; MU-2388 (Box 18)
      Cream tankard Cornell emblem
    - Cornell Class of 1920 65th reunion mug, 1985; MU-2368a-2368b (Box 19)
      White mug with emblem. Made in Trenton NJ
    - Cornell Class of 1945 40th reunion tankard, 1985; MU-2369 (Box 18)
      Cream tankard with Cornell emblem
    - Cornell Class of 1945 40th reunion tankard, 1985; MU-1317-1318 (Box 18)
    - Cornell Class of 1945 35th reunion tankard, 1980; MU-1315-1316 (Box 18)
      Cream tankard with black Cornell emblem
    - Cornell Class of 1945 45th reunion tankard, 1990; MU-1319-1320 (Box 22)
    - Cornell Class of 1983 10th reunion champagne flute, 1993; MU-1282-1283 (Box 17)
    - Class of 1987 Wine tumbler, 1987; MU-2392a-2392b (Box 17)
  - Subseries IIb. Fraternities, Societies, and Schools
    - Sigma Alpha Mu tankard, 1934; MU-2466 (Box 22)
    - Cosmopolitan Club cup, Undated; MU-562, MU-1180a, MU-1299, MU-1368, MU-2468a-x (Box 24, 25)
    - Cosmopolitan Club saucer, Undated; MU-563, MU-1180b (Box 23, 24)
    - Cosmopolitan Club saucers, Undated; MU-2467a-kk (Box 23, 24)
      Makers mark B-1
    - Cornell Alembic mug, Undated; MU-2341 (Box 20)
      Cream ceramic mug with Alembic written in Arabic in gold image of an alembic
    - College of Law mug, 1903; MU-1222 (Box 21)
      CL '03 in red on one side, Cornell emblem in red on the other side
    - Cornell Junior Law Smoker, 1906; MU-997 (Box 21)
      Cream mug
    - Cornell Law Senior Smoker, 1906; MU-998
      Ivory mug with image of man and a stein
    - College of Law Smoker mug, 1908; MU-2342 (Box 19)
    - College of Law Smoker mug, 1909; MU-2345 (Box 22)
    - College of Law Smoker mug, 1910; MU-1225, MU-2344 (Box 19)
    - Chemists' Feed, 1912; MU-2355-2356 (Box 20)
    - College of Agriculture and Life Sciences, Undated; MU-1145 (Box 19)
      "We Grow the Ivy"
    - Cornell Co-op dining mug, MU-126 (Box 21)
      "Food for Thought"
    - Cornell Crew mug, MU-2459a-2459b (Box 18)
      Green-rimmed mug with image of man with oar, by Avon W.R. Co
    - Thirsty Bear Tavern 7th anniversary plastic mug, Undated; MU-1279-1281 (Box 22)
    - Pi Lambda Phi tankard, 1944; MU-2389 (Box 22)
      Cream tankard with emblem and "Mort" written on side
    - Plastic Library coffee mug, Undated; MU-1113 (Box 19)
    - Plastic Cornell coffee mug, Undated; MU-2083 (Box 22)
    - Cornell Computer Science 50 years mug, Undated; MU-2391 (Box 22)
    - Statler Club mug, Undated; MU-2461 (Box 19)
    - Tau Delta Eta tankard with "Annie" written in gold, 1958; MU-2465 (Box 22)
  - Subseries IIc. General Cornell Cups and Mugs
    - Cornell Yell mug, 1909; MU-1366 (Box 21)
      Cream mug with "Cornell I yell-yell-yell Cornell", Cornell emblem with two flags, and "'09" in red
    - Cornell Yell mug, Undated; MU-2354 (Box 19)
      White mug with six imgages of Cornell buildings, "Cornell I Yell Yell Yell, Far Above Cayuga's Waters" in red
    - "Ba-Tum-Zup" mug, 1912-05-18; MU-2360 (Box 20)
    - Handmade mug with man in car above McGraw Tower, 1912; MU-2366 (Box 18)
      Handmade by Henry Bollman, East Gloucester Mass.
    - Glass Cornell mug, Undated; MU-1285 (Box 17)
      Clear glass with gray and gold emblem
    - Cornell University milk bottle, Undated; MU-214 (Box 17)
      Half pint clear glass bottle with embossed C.U.
    - Cornell University mug, 1993; MU-1157 (Box 21)
      Cream mug with black, gold, and red emblem
    - Cornell University mug, 1996; MU-1158 (Box 21)
      Cream mug with Gold and red emblem
    - Cornell University mug, 1997; MU-1159 (Box 21)
    - Cornell University mug, 1999; MU-1160 (Box 21)
    - Cornell University mug, 2001; MU-1161 (Box 21)
    - Cornell University mug, 2003; MU-1162-1163 (Box 21)
    - Cornell University tankard, Undated; MU-1321 (Box 22)
      Cream tankard with red Cornell emblem
    - Cognac glass with gold Cornell emblem, Undated; MU-2353a-2353b (Box 17)
    - Highball glass with Cornell emblem and silver rim, Undated; MU-2347a-2347b (Box 17)
    - Tumbler glass with Cornell emblem and silver rim, Undated; MU-2349a-2349b (Box 17)
    - Highball glass with red and white Cornell emblem, Undated; MU-2351a-2351b (Box 17)
    - Highball glass with red Cornell emblem, Undated; MU-2352a-2352b (Box 17)
    - Cornell Alumni Reunion tin mug, 1962; MU-2371a-2371b (Box 20)
    - Cornell Alumni Reunion tin mug, 1963; MU-2372 (Box 20)
    - Cornell Alumni Reunion tin mug, 1964; MU-2385a-2385b (Box 20)
    - Cornell Alumni Reunion tin mug, 1966; MU-421-422 (Box 20)
    - Cornell Alumni Reunion tin mug, 1969; MU-2374 (Box 18)
    - Cornell Class Reunion tin mug, 1970; MU-1322a-1322b (Box 18)
    - Cornell Class Reunion tin mug, 1971; MU-2386 (Box 18)
    - Cornell Class Reunion tin mug, 1972; MU-2373a-2373b (Box 18)
    - Cornell Class Reunion tin mug, 1974; MU-2387a-2387b (Box 18)
    - Tin mug with Cornell C and lion, Undated; MU-1306 (Box 20)
    - Cornell Class Reunion tin mug, 1949; MU-1307, MU-2384 (Box 18)
    - Cornell glass, 1865-1965 with emblem, 1965; MU-1284 (Box 17)
- Series III. Cornell Plates (non-Wedgwood)
  - Souvenir plate showing 7 campus scenes, 1893-1910; Mu-578, MU-216 (Box 26)
    Flow blue plates by Rowland and Marsellus Co.
  - Plate with Cornell emblem in center and 6 building scenes, 1904-06; MU-216 (Box 26)
    Hallmarks: Royal Doulton England, Rothschild Bros., Ithaca NY
  - Clear glass plate with "Cornell" etched on, Undated; MU-2501 (Box 27)
  - "Libe" tower plate, Undated; MU-2048 (Box 26)
    Image of McGraw tower in red in center, gold trim. American Decorators, Inc. Trenton NJ
  - Painted plate with image of New York State Agriculture School, Undated; MU-1077 (Box 27)
    Made in Germany
  - Red-rimmed plate, Undated; MU-1076 (Box 27)
    Red and gold emblem in the center, Schwarzburg hallmark
  - Cornell Cooperative Extension Seventy-fifth Anniversary Banquet, 1986-06-06; MU-1121 (Box 26)
  - Library Tower image ash tray, Undated; MU-2502 (Box 27)